<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Avaritia coram tribunali: or, the miser arraign'd at the bar of scripture and reason for his sinful neglect of charity, in this present lamentable and dreadful visitation of the plague. By a gentleman that loves men more than money.</title>
            <author>Gentleman that loves men more than money.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1666</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75822</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A4266</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223581</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899750</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899750</idno>
            <idno type="VID">133593</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75822)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 133593)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2433:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Avaritia coram tribunali: or, the miser arraign'd at the bar of scripture and reason for his sinful neglect of charity, in this present lamentable and dreadful visitation of the plague. By a gentleman that loves men more than money.</title>
                  <author>Gentleman that loves men more than money.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Elizabeth Calvert, and are to be sold at the Black-spread-Eagle, at the west end of S. Paul's,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1666.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Plague --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:133593:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133593:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133593:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133593:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Avaritia coram Tribunali:</hi> OR, The Miſer arraign'd AT The Bar of Scripture and Reaſon; For his ſinful neglect of Charity, in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent lamentable and dreadful Viſitation Of the PLAGUE.</p>
            <p>By a Gentleman that loves Men more than Money.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good works, and glorifie your Father which is in heaven,</p>
               <bibl>S. Mat. 5.16.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>He that ſoweth little, ſhall reap little; and he that ſoweth plenteouſly, ſhall reap plenteouſly. Let every man do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as he is diſpoſed in his heart, not grudgingly, or of neceſsity; for God loveth a cheerful giver,</p>
               <bibl>2 Cor. 9.6,7.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Sen.</bibl> Hoc habent Homines cum Diis commune, ut aliis Benefecerint.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Elizabeth Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Black-ſpread-Eagle, at the Weſt End of S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s. 1666.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:133593:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:133593:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Avaritia coram Tribunali:</hi> OR, The MISER arraign'd at the BAR OF SCRIPTURE and REASON.</head>
            <p>IT is no news to perſons who have delighted themſelves with the pleaſant and profitable converſation of a Library, That the World is ſo imperious a Critick, that the firſt thing an Epiſtle commonly preſents the Reader, is, A complemental Excuſe for troubling him. Importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Friends; ſurreptitious Copies; to ſpend my idle time, or gratifie my good friend the <hi>Stationer;</hi> &amp; other ſuch-like Sconces (commonly built to defend Caſtles in the Air) are the hackney Defences againſt the Ruſtick Battery of Ignorance, and her Daughter Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence; of Detraction, and her Mother Envy. But the beſt friend to ſuch pretenſions, is a Socratical Ingenuouſneſs; <hi>Erubuit ſalva res eſt;</hi> The young Blade bluſhes, and all is well: Let not the moroſe melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly of a Study put in Interrogatories, Shall friends ſeduce a man a degree or two on this ſide a Phrenſie,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:133593:4"/> to run the Gauntlet? How many have you known <hi>tam curtae ſupellectilis,</hi> ſo ill furniſhed as to want Trunks ſuſticient to contain their own Papers? <hi>O Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pora! O Mores!</hi> Is not Idleneſs the Fools Largeſs? and do Grocers and Cooks want waſte-Paper? <hi>Sed non tibi notus Ulyſſes;</hi> there's a fetch for applauſe beyond all this, A pretence of Publick Good, which avoyds many ſtrict examinations, with that ordinary Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, <hi>Bonum quo communius, eo melius;</hi> and indeed this Apology (when the Chaff of Hypocriſie is fann'd away) is the Chriſtian Author's compleat Armor, whereby his devout Thoughts are left invulnerable, not onely againſt pragmatical Cenſure, but Principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and Powers, and all the ſinful works of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: and how can popular breath, though never ſo ſharp and impetuous, force him to an ignoble flight, who (through Gods diſcriminating grace and favour) has reſolutely fix'd the Eye of his Diſcourſe upon his Creators glory, and the benefit of his Neighbour; which word under the interpretation of an unbyaſs'd Conſcience and ſincere Heart, is as comprehenſive and univerſal as Humanity it ſelf? <hi>Feciſti Domine Cor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter te, &amp; irrequietum eſt donec perveniat ad te,</hi> ſaid the holy Biſhop of <hi>Hippo.</hi> Give me <hi>Aquinas,</hi> take you <hi>Scotus;</hi> give me <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> take you <hi>Des Cartes:</hi> Does a Pen trace <hi>Galen,</hi> or ruffling <hi>Paracelſus?</hi> yet the <hi>Laco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian Ti</hi> may ſerve to anſwer King <hi>Philip,</hi> and ſcoff all tuggers at the Quill. If your endeavours prove for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate, then
<q>
                  <l>Digito monſtrarier, &amp; dicier hic est:</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:133593:4"/>
               <q>
                  <l>This, this is he, ſtretch'd-out fore-fingers tell,</l>
                  <l>Writ that brave Piece which ſold ſo wondrous well.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But not a few learned Men could I ſummon in to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie how skittiſh our Age is, how apt to ſtart, how apt to ſtumble; ſo that <hi>Irrequieta eſt Penna tuo, donec perveniat ad Deum.</hi> All ſublunary Tranſactions have no other Inſurance-Office then the Providence of the Almighty: when his Honour and Service are the Marks levell'd at, then we quickly diſcern it to be true Philoſophy, that the whole Earth is but as an indiviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble point, compared to the Heavens. What matter who derides? what matter who reviles? canſt clap thy Breſt, and talk in <hi>Apelles</hi> ſtrain, <hi>Pingo Eternitati;</hi> then (in the Scripture-Language) gird up thy Loins, and be ſtrong; the Fountain of Goodneſs can never turn Bankrupt; and that by S. <hi>Paul</hi> inſures thy Barque, at leaſt to the Port of everlaſting Happineſs, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.58. <hi>Therefore, my beloved Brethren, be ye ſtedfast, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable, always abounding in the work of the Lord; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as ye know that your labor is not in vain in the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the deſtroying Angel brandiſhes his Sword over our <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the Peſtilence has already ſhot in many terrible and barbed Arrows of Divine Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance; certainly he muſt have very little ſenſe of his own Offences, and the whole Nations both Crime and Puniſhment, that can't afford a ſigh, a tear, and <hi>God be merciful unto us, for we have ſinned.</hi> When many thouſands have died ſince <hi>April,</hi> 7496 is found at the foot of the laſt Weekly Bill; and many, very many
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:133593:5"/> of their lives might have been preſerved (as a great Bleſſing to their Relations) if <hi>rich men</hi> were but <hi>Men;</hi> if they would but <hi>live</hi> till they <hi>dy'd;</hi> not deſerve <hi>Hic ſitus est,</hi> an Epitaph a long while before the Mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners go about the ſtreets. It can't undoubtedly be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted unprofitable ſpending my hours on this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Faſt-day (the ſixth of <hi>September</hi>) if I plead in <hi>Forma Pauperis,</hi> and voluntarily undertake <hi>Timothy</hi>'s hard task, 1 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 6.17,18. <hi>Charge them that are rich in this world, that they be not high-minded, nor truſt in uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain riches, but in the living God, who gives us richly all things to enjoy; that they do good, that they be rich in good works, ready to diſtribute, willing to communicate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not be ſo magiſterial, as to affirm this and that particular ſin was the root of our Thorns and Briers, for I am none of the Sons of <hi>Aaron;</hi> nor if I were, ſhould I preſume to ſnatch my faint and glim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mering Candle out of the dark Lanthorn of ſilence and obſcurity, when our holy Mother the Church has advanc'd her Torch in a neceſſary, pious, ſeaſonable Exhortation: Yet ſince People count it as it were cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomary for their reſpective Miniſters to perſwade Contributions; and Apples of Gold in Pictures of Silver, may want their due reverence with the many, by reaſon of unwelcom reiteration; it will be no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervice to the Pulpit, if they find an Eccho in a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey Receſs: and poſſibly ſome or other may mind it, introduc'd with theſe circumſtantial conſiderations, That 'tis good will to all in poverty and woful per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity, and not either ſelfiſh deſign, or home-bred caſualties, that form the rebound.</p>
            <p>We will begin our Memoyrs, by taking notice that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:133593:5"/> Children (who can't be ſuſpected for <hi>Machiavilians</hi>) are accounted of good diſpoſition by all, when they are willing to part with this or that trifle they may be call'd Owners of. By this we may eaſily conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture what humane Nature is, before it be eſtray'd too far from Innocencie, and has drunk too deep of the <hi>Marah</hi> of bad Education and evil Cuſtoms. At mature years, Noble Houſe-keeping is the characte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtical Letter of Generoſity. What more apt or uſual expreſſion, than to call a coverous Perſon, <hi>A nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Soul;</hi> and, as one tartly expreſſes it, <hi>fit to live no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where but in an Ally?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Can a ſerious and deliberate Head give Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to his Tongue to call <hi>Veſpaſian,</hi> The Darling of Mankinde, and yet forget the uſual Sentence that dub'd him ſo? <hi>Diem perdidi: My unlimited Soveraignty, my tranſcendent Glory has not diſtill'd upon my Subjects any reviving ſhowers of Grace and Munificence; I have lost this day. The men of Nineveh</hi> (ſayes our ever-bleſſed Saviour) <hi>ſhall riſe in Judgement againſt this generation, and condemn it:</hi> And do ſober Chriſtians imagine that the High and Mighty Monarch of the diſcover'd World ſhould bewayl the loſs of twenty four hours, for fear of diſpleaſing burniſh'd Braſs, and carved Wood; and he not call'd to a ſevere account by the Ancient of Days, for bringing forth nothing in it, may be more then four and twenty years, but drouzy Poppy, inſtead of the ſtaff of Bread; ſowr Grapes and wild Olives? But admit that even according to the Pſalmiſts Arithmetick, your foot be not yet in the Grave, and decripped Age is by moſt deſigned for the ſtall of Repentance; yet you cannot convict your
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:133593:6"/> ſecurity by the Verdict of a wiſer than <hi>Solomon, Eccl.</hi> 11.9. <hi>Rejoyce O young man in thy youth, and let thy Heart chear thee in the days of thy youth, and walk in the ways of thy heart, and in the ſight of thine eyes; but know thou that for all theſe things God will bring thee into Judgement.</hi> The Angelical Doctor obſerves, That Death is a more treacherous Enemy in ſurpriſing youth by ſtratagem, ſtealing upon them unawares, when their Backs are towards it; than to the grey-heads, whom it charges on the front; and the dimmer their eyes be, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they may diſcern a Coffin: the more cauſe they have to cry out, <hi>O curva ſenectus,</hi> O ſhrinking ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, O feeble knees, the more is the Grave obvious, and conſequently might be rendered more familiar. May a ſpring of warm blood full of ſpirits, by three or four fits of an Ague, be ſadly metamorphos'd into ſhivering <hi>December,</hi> a pale Cheek, a dull Eye, a ſoft pace, a reſtleſs Bed? Can a Feaver (even without the help of an univerſally-deſtroying putrefaction of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours) ſhake off golden Locks (thoſe beautiful leaves of the <hi>Arbor Inverſa</hi>) ſcorch up the radical moyſture, baniſh the poor Creature into the land of forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and make an humble Turf the diſhonourable Coverlet of an Airy Gallant, of a rare-accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh'd Monſieur? And can Summer, Autumn, Winter, expect fairer uſage? Can they that have enjoy'd a large Eſtate many inches of the longeſt ſpan of Life, conceive it not yet high time to make friends of unrighteous <hi>Mammon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We need not deſire a Legat <hi>Kekerman,</hi> to repair to his beloved <hi>Dichotomie,</hi> about diviſion of Eſtates; they may logically enough to our purpoſe be ſaid to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:133593:6"/> come by divine Providence: but nevertheleſs it will not be amiſs to keep the road, and take for our fellow-travellers <hi>Deſcent</hi> and <hi>Purchaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He that has digg'd himſelf thirty or forty years to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the golden <hi>Peru</hi> of Profit, ſhould do very well to conſider whether his hands be not dirty; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Widdow and the Orphan, this weak Brain, and that credulous Tenant, Clyent, Cuſtomer, have no juſt cauſe to complain of his gripes; though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance nor well vers'd how to remedy themſelves: If ſo, how fence you this blow of the Caſuiſts, <hi>Without Reſtitution no Salvation?</hi> Delay not, unleſs thou art content to endure the gnawings of the Worm of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience at thy diſſolution, when Horror and Amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment cry out, <hi>Haſt thou found me, O mine Enemy?</hi> Nor could that ſuffice the converted Publican <hi>Zacheus;</hi> he reſtor'd four-fold to heal the wound of Extortion, and gave half that he had to the poor, to prevent a ſcarre. If the pamper'd fleſh turns a deaf ear, and the deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful World ſearches Hell for diſtinctions, carry them both to <hi>Tho. à Kempis</hi> Cell; <hi>Durum eſt verbum</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>tolle crucem &amp; ſequere me; ſed multo durius, Ite male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicti in ignem ſempiternum:</hi> 'Tis an hard Chapter, <hi>Take up your croſs and follow me;</hi> but 'tis a far more intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>Go ye curſed into everlasting fire.</hi> Are you behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to a rich Anceſtor for thoſe Rivolets of Milk and Honey that bedew your condition? then God has gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven you Preſs-money in hand; and a ſuperabundant gratitude engages to manage your Stewardſhip with fidelity, and to imploy your Talents with an induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Zeal. Riſing early, going to Bed late, in conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with the Bread of carefulneſs, are ſtrangers to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:133593:7"/> your Birthright: Would you ſtand idle in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket all day long, and that after you have received your penny? God gave you not Honour and Wealth to furniſh a magazine for rebellious vices, blacker in the eyes of Heaven, then any Ink can render their names. Deceitful, diſorderly, and exceſſive Gaming, put the preſent Parliament (in the ſixteenth of our moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Sovereign) to the trouble of an Act to reſtrain it; from which it is evident that one hundred pound was before look'd upon as nothing to loſe and run up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Tick at a time; <hi>Diſcinctis nepotibus,</hi> with my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant young Maſters: one time might be one mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute; but ſhould one of thoſe A-la-mode Quakers, or Shakers, give ſo much in ſeven years to the relief of the poor and afflicted, he would not to be ſure change <hi>Soul take thine eaſe,</hi> but inſtead of <hi>Thou haſt goods laid up for many years</hi> (for that were a Sarcaſm of his own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting) would laugh in his ſleeve, and hug the phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, that he had done good deeds enough for many years, yes even for <hi>Methuſelah</hi>'s 969. But all Eſtates are <hi>Dominica Coronae Reg is Coelestis,</hi> belong to the King of Kings; His is <hi>directum Dominium,</hi> an abſolute and uncontroulable Regality: the Poſterity of <hi>Adam</hi> have onely <hi>Utile Dominium;</hi> ſo that we may truly ſay, not onely, <hi>Lord, thou haſt made us, and not we our ſelves;</hi> but, <hi>Lord, our Inheritances are thine, and not our own. The Earth is the Lords, and all the fulneſs thereof:</hi> this Lump of <hi>Clay</hi> he has made a Veſſel of Honour, that of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour; ſome fit objects of <hi>Charity,</hi> and others his <hi>Almoners.</hi> Aska fellow as abſuedly prodigal as a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain rich Citizens Heir, (whom ſome alive remember a petty <hi>Prince</hi> in the morning of his Age, and a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicable
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:133593:7"/> 
               <hi>Beggar</hi> before noon) who for fear of a ſurfeit of <hi>Wealth</hi> made Ducks &amp; Drakes (in the Childrens Bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) with Six-pences, Shillings and Half-crowns, in the <hi>Thames;</hi> or a fellow as ridiculouſly covetous as he in the <hi>Comedy,</hi> that ſtop'd the top of his Chimney for fear of loſing the ſmoak, few of either Herd will deny that <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaid true, <hi>The lot is cast into the lap, but the whole diſpoſing thereof is of the Lord;</hi> or that of <hi>Job, The Lord gives, and the Lord takes away:</hi> but depraved Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture muſters up Quirks to avoid the Statute <hi>de Donis conditionalibus,</hi> in the Bible; and will by no means al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that <hi>voluntas omnipotentis Donatoris, ſecundum for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam in charta Doni ſui manifestè expreſſam obſervaretur:</hi> That the intent and good pleaſure of the omnipotent Donor, plainly expreſſed in thoſe ſacred leaves of his revealed Will, ſhould be punctually obſerved: a moſt clear and ſignificant <hi>Precept</hi> take from <hi>Deut.</hi> 15.7,8. <hi>If there be among you a poor man, of one of thy Brethren, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in any of thy gates, in thy Land which the Lord thy God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth thee; thou ſhalt not harden thine heart, nor ſhut thy hand from thy poor Brother; but thou ſhalt open thine hand wide unto him, and ſhalt ſurely lend him ſufficient for his need, in that which he wanteth. Deut.</hi> 26.12,13. about the third years tything: will you have a comment? read Dr. <hi>Hamond</hi>'s Sermon: I ſhall quote little from him, and what I do, leave it like <hi>Eſops</hi> provident Fathers Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in the Vineyard; who told his Sons it was hid there, but ſaid no more, on purpoſe that they might dig and ranſack every foot. After that eminent Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor has prov'd <hi>Charity</hi> to be like a <hi>Picture,</hi> looking up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every one that comes into the great Room of the World; he kills the Bugbear of old Age, and the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:133593:8"/> of <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> againſt the moſt laudable disburſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, namely, the fear of want; by aſſerting <hi>Davids</hi> Doctrine in ſeveral pious inferences: <hi>They that give un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the poor, lend unto the Lord; and he will repay it.</hi> To whom firſt? To the Houſhold of Faith: Where chiefly? To our Neighbourhood, before places more remote: When? Whenſoever we meet with an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity; or by a prudent ſeparation of this and the other Sheaf of our Revenue, are inabled to ſeek one. But let his own words adminiſter advice againſt the ſpirit of Slumber, that <hi>Chyragra</hi> of the Worldling, as to Eleemoſynary Land-marks: <hi>The proportion to be obſerved by the Chriſtian Almes-giver, to ſpeak at the leaſt, muſt be more in any reaſon then the thirtieth part of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue or Increaſe. Non magna loquimur, ſed vivimus;</hi> He preach'd no more than he liv'd; nor ſo much nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for he gave the tenth part to the Poor conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, beſides the ſpring-tides of his extraordinary ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-heartedneſs and compaſſion. I wiſh we could all as eaſily imitate his Life, as procure a Treatiſe ſo called (a Piece of ſtrong lines, and good complexion) But if ever ye deſire to converſe with the Saint, as well as viſit the Shrine; trace him by his own Counſel, Offer unto God the Sacrifice of a contrite Heart, and the ſweet incenſe of univerſal Obedience.</p>
            <p>The neceſſities of Men, trivial Follies, and that great one, Perverſneſs, have produc'd a multitude of caſes in Law, of unlike features; ſo that 'tis not to be expected a Maxim ſhould knock down every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar occurrence with a <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> fiſt, <hi>Concluſum eſt contra Manichaeos;</hi> that the Rule ſhould aſcertain po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively either the Affirmative or Negative: But from
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:133593:8"/> general Gounds and Eruditions, a learned Inference, a ſmart Deduction, muſt ſtate the matter in agitation. VVe have in the Goſpel Line upon Line, and Precept upon Precept, to command us to put on Brotherly Kindneſs, and the Bowels of Compaſſion; but ſhould we disband our Vantguard of direct and demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Texts, the proceedings of the day of Judgement afford Inſtructions clearer than the Sun in his Mid-Summer-Glory, and printed in ſuch Elephantine-Characters, that whoſo runs may read them, S <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.35. Giving Meat to the Hungry, Drink to the Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, Lodging to the Stranger, Cloaths to the Naked, Viſits to the Sick, Redemption to Captives, are aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned as the reaſon of that triumphant Invitation, <hi>verſ.</hi> 24. <hi>Then ſhall the King ſay unto them on his right hand, Come ye bleſſed of my Father, inherit the Kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the world.</hi> Leave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his 600 choſen Chariots at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of the Red Sea, <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Jezebel</hi> to the Dogs, <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> to his Halter; great and notorious Sinners to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary puniſhments here; (although Thunderbolts kill not often) or at leaſt unleſs the generation of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers repent, and fly from the wrath to come, to the horrid and racking expectation of the ſecond death: come hither harmleſs well-meaning Chriſtian, gather the bitter fruit of Omiſſion, and diſſect the barren womb of Holineſs with this Inſtrument, <hi>verſ.</hi> 41. <hi>Then ſhall he ſay alſo unto them on his left hand, Depart from me ye curſed, into everlaſting fire prepared for the Devil and his Angels. Watch and pray, for ye know not at what hour your Lord will come:</hi> but it is evident what our Lord will ſay when he does come to judge every man accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:133593:9"/> to what he has done in the Body, whether good or evil. Wife Virgins know the Bridegroom loves the Oyl of Mercy; they will upon no terms ſhew ſuch want of civility and vulgar manners, as to have their Lamps to light, when he paſſeth by; eſpecially ſince the fire of <hi>Charity</hi> devours not the unctious humour, no more than the Prophet <hi>Elijah</hi>'s Hunger emptied the Widow of <hi>Zarephath</hi>'s Cruſe. Fear of a conſumption of the Purſe, through that excellent and ſucceſsful Phlebotomy, is routed by the heavenly Hoſt of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes: Queſtionleſs that inexorable Gluttons part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.19. who treated the Bru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e his Carcaſe ſumptuouſly every day, has onely <hi>Animam pro ſale,</hi> a Soul to keep his Body from ſtinking, till Death locks up the Purple in the Wardrobe, allowing onely the fine Linen of a Winding-Sheet, and then ſerves him up to the Worms; muſt at laſt change the frolick Scene to weeping and gnaſhing of teeth. The ſooty fumes aſcending from an impure ſtomach, cauſes the brain to want ſweeping, the whole unprofitable maſs to want evacuation; from whence naturally ariſes ſtupidity and unactiveneſs, and then ſtrutting about, and yawning:
<q>
                  <l>Pleno laudat Jejunia ventre:</l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>The Churle is cramm'd; his Paraſite cann't carve</l>
                  <l>One tempting bit: Steal Poor, be hang'd, beg, ſtarve.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But there will come a time, or rather an eternity, when <hi>Lazarus,</hi> who by reaſon of age, ſickneſs, a charge of ſmall Children, loſſes by Sea or Fire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was compell'd to imitate the diſconſolate murmurs of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:133593:9"/> the Turtle, and (being far beneath the ownerſhip of a Couch) water'd his ſtraw every night with tears; though he might not divide the ſpoyl with the Dogs, in ſharing part of the crumbs that fell from the Rich Mans Table, ſhall be mounted up into <hi>Abrahams Boſom</hi> upon the Wings of glorious Spirits; when ſottiſh, flint-hearted-<hi>Dives,</hi> ſhall not obtain with his earneſt and vehement begging, the tip of a wet finger to cool his Tongue that was tormented in the flame, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually frying in the bottomleſs Pit, that inexhauſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble lake of Fire and Brimſtone.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charity</hi> is a comprehenſive word, and like the <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terranean Sea,</hi> acquires ſeveral names from the adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent ſhores: <hi>Mercy, Almes, Liberality, Beneficence,</hi> all fall under that title, and may not unfitly be look'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as onely ſeveral degrees of heat, and alterations of the ſame ineſtimable Elixar. Let the Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſay, There ſtands a deplorable Object; Mercy, from a cold Still, preſently melts into a drop or two of Silver: If exquiſite Education, and a perception that the vertue of money lies onely in its ſubſerviency to commerce, and the mutual neceſſities of the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of this terreſtrial Globe; put a merciful diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition into a Limbeck, then this and the other Bag will be thought well ſpent in generous Hoſpitality; and <hi>Sundayes, Tueſdayes</hi> and <hi>Thurſdayes,</hi> (provided the Cook-Maid be in a good mood) half a dozen of the poor of the Pariſh, may fill their Bellies after a faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But ſtill here's the head of the <hi>Crow,</hi> a black ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment at the bottom; an Ox or two at <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> a feaſt now and then for Tenants, a diſh extraordinary at command, to prevent the ſurprize of Acquaintance;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:133593:10"/> and then call me Niggard who dare. But when from being good in an humour, and doing good by fits; Vertue proceeds from ſingle Acts to an Habit; from an Habit, to an Heroical Exaltation; a beam of the Sun of Righteouſneſs that ariſes with healing in his Wings infus'd, will produce the pure and unvaluable crimſon Tincture; and make the Artiſt cry out, <hi>I deſire to know nothing but Jeſus Chriſt, and him crucified.</hi> All the Income (though never ſo vaſt) will bear the Image and Superſcription of the heavenly <hi>Caeſar;</hi> and every day yeilds precious opportunities of exchang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his <hi>Jacobuſſes</hi> and <hi>Gynnyes</hi> to the <hi>New Jeruſalem;</hi> whoſe Street is pure Gold, and whoſe Gates are Pearls; where Ruſt cannot corrupt, nor Thieves break through, and ſteal.</p>
            <p>But for my part, I ſhall neither uſurp the Divines <hi>Chair,</hi> nor domineer in the Peripatetick <hi>School;</hi> this Meditation is ambitious of no higher preferment, then to be Uſher to the Basket, and call aloud, <hi>For Gods ſake remember the Poor.</hi> A Duty at all times ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable; in this Huge Mortality, Clamerouſly urgent. <hi>The Poor you have alwayes with you;</hi> but never had a more amazing Argument to frequent the Offertory, to give the Overſeers meaſure preſt down, and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning over. <hi>Auguſta eſt Charitas ad Leges vincta;</hi> A Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial Tax, A Monthly Collection, adde the Free-will Offerings of here and there a Star of the firſt, ſecond, and third Magnitude, (whoſe Names let Hiſtory convey to the Temple of Honour, and there Engrave in a Marble Column;) all conjoyn'd, are too narrow, and too weak Emplaiſters to be applyed to all the Plague-Sores (that deſerve Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeration,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:133593:10"/> and want the ordinary means of Cure) in the 130 Pariſhes of <hi>London,</hi> and many Country-Towns, and Villages; unleſs the Phyſitian wanted no more chargeable Drugs, than the Royal Prophet <hi>Iſaiahs lump of Figs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Skin for skin, and all a man hath will he give for his Life;</hi> was the ſharpeſt Tooth, and ſtrongeſt Paw, wherewith the Roaring Lyon <hi>Satan,</hi> aſſaulted the Integrity of <hi>Job. Ventum erat ad Triarios;</hi> the Devil was driven to his laſt charge, when he fell on ſo fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly. But though ſo many hundreds have drunk the dregs of the Lords Wrath, (as to the temporal Vial) and that City which was lately the Joy and Delight of the whole Nation, is turn'd into a kinde of <hi>Golgotha,</hi> and like dejected <hi>Rachel,</hi> ſits with diſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel'd Hair, weeping, and mourning, and will not be comforted becauſe her Children are not; Yet, <hi>Ille meos oculos comprimat, Ille tuos;</hi> It were a Cordial to the gaſping Patient, if a diſcreet Friend might draw his Will; this dear Son, or Daughter, or the other Affectionate Kinſman might cloſe his Eyes, and pulling the Curtains cloſe, Modeſtly hide the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formities of a ruin'd Cottage, from impertinent Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity. But, <hi>Hinc ille Lachrymae!</hi> Infected perſons can't expect Viſiters; and the ſpur of Fear hurries away Neighbours (of any Quality) ſo faſt, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they come to their rural Sanctuaries, they have ſcarce leaſure to afford the kindneſs of <hi>Lots</hi> Wife to <hi>Sodom,</hi> a pitiful Retroſpection.</p>
            <p>The greateſt cruelty the Poet could brand a Tyrant with, was,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:133593:11"/>
               <q>
                  <l>Mortua—jungebat Corpora vivis.</l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>Quick ty'd to Dead, were hurl'd to ſeek their Graves,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Neptunes</hi> Executioners, the Waves.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Not the Tyranny, but merciful Wiſdom of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, concludes it neceſſary to ſhut up the whole Family; not onely the Sick, but the Well; for, <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet anguis in Herba,</hi> all fleſh is graſs, and be it never ſo green, the Conſtitution ſtrong, and florid, yet in a few dayes the ſting of Contagion may wound under the fifth Rib; the Throat may rattle, the Pulſe ceaſe, and Duſt return to Duſt. Nor may they which ſeem in Health be permitted to ſtraggle, leſt the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Diſeaſe ſhould Rob in the open Street, and Kings Highway; juſtles be Fatal, ſalutations Dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. It is remarqued concerning <hi>Holland,</hi> that 'tis a kinde of a Courteſie for the Poor to be put in Priſon, becauſe the rich Creditors are bound to provide for them. But in many caſes there's no Juſtice in that, for Lazineſs, and Brandy might contract, and a reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Importunity extort the Debt. But, <hi>Actus Dei nemini facit Injuria;</hi> without diſpute they ought to be carefully provided for, that loſe Liberty; (the dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Sublunary enjoyments, and Favourite of the Law;) and are made Priſoners by the angry diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of God; and not by their own Idleneſs, and Debauchery.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sir <hi>Walter Rawley. Judge Jenkins.</hi>
               </note> We are beholden to the <hi>Fleet,</hi> for <hi>Fleta.</hi> To the <hi>Tower,</hi> for an Incomparable Hiſtory. And <hi>Newgate</hi> it ſelf, in our unhappy
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:133593:11"/> Civil War, could cry out, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Laws written by the Finger of God in Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of Stone, nor thoſe of <hi>England,</hi> (which may challenge a modeſt Eternity <hi>ex parte ante,</hi> as having their Original hid like the Head of <hi>Nilus,</hi> in the folds of Antiquity;) will allow Subjects to take up Arms againſt their King.</p>
            <p>The Soul may <hi>Aethereas volitare per Auras,</hi> take the freſh Aire, and like the <hi>Bee</hi> ſuck Hony out of variety of Claſſick Authors; when the Body is confin'd, and like a Tennis-Ball toſs'd from Hazard to Hazard, in a Solitary Walk, from this, to the oppoſite Wall, of a Dark, Pittiful Chamber: But how can they who have the Peſtilence for their Goaler, alleviate the preſſures of an unhappy Condition by a ſweet Thought, or brisker Meditation? They ſit like <hi>Niobe</hi> turn'd to Stones; or if great Grief can ſpeak, it is in <hi>Jeremiahs</hi> Dialect; <hi>Is it nothing to you, all ye that paſs by,</hi> (To your Country-houſes, and are no more heard of till the Tempeſt be over?) <hi>behold and ſee if there be any ſorrow, like unto my ſorrow; which is done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Me; wherewith the Lord hath afflicted Me in the day of his fierce Anger?</hi> Lam. 1.12.</p>
            <p>Burning is the Puniſhment of great and heynous Malefactors; and yet that's the Epithite of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Feaver. If the diſmal Ingredient of prevailing Venom be added to the Trophy of a leſs obſervable Cholerick Putrefaction, the Meazles, and Small-Pox (borrowing the Future tence from <hi>Eliſhas</hi> curſe,) make a <hi>Gehazi;</hi> a Leper, from the Crown of the Head, to the Sole of the Foot; and 'tis well if at laſt he eſcapes alive from the Pot-ſheards, and the Dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:133593:12"/>
            <p>A more Rampant Malignity generates the Spotted-Feaver. But if the Pale Horſe of Death ruſhes more outragiouſly into the Battle, and tramples upon his Thouſands, and ten Thonſands, then the <hi>Plague,</hi> (that <hi>Attila</hi> of Diſeaſes) haraſes City, and Country; and <hi>Michael</hi> the Angel of Vengeance (in ſpight of the <hi>Rabbins</hi> Proverb) has two Wings, as well as <hi>Gabriel;</hi> and ſtrikes whole Legions, <hi>cum Flagello Domini,</hi> with the Scorpions of incenſed Juſtice; Imprinting Botches under the Ears, and about the Neck; Blains of a Straw-colour, and Broniſh Blew; fiery and corroding Carbuncles; Party-colour'd ſpots on the Breaſt, Back, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All which may be termed not onely <hi>Ingraveſcentis Morbi, ſed Peccatorum Indices;</hi> not onely the ſymptoms of a Spreading and Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulating Plague, but the Tokens of Indignation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſtiff-necked, and ſtubborn Generation; whom odious and unnatural Broyls could not terrifie from the ſuperfluity of Naughtineſs; nor the Olive-branch of Peace, and a return from Captivity allure to a Spiritual (well if to a Vocal) <hi>Te Deum Laudamus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let us Rentour Hearts, and not our Garments; acknowledge our Tranſgreſſions, and ſet our Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties before us; doubtleſs we that have cumbred the Ground long, (though Glory be to God on High, we are not yet cut down) are as great ſinners as thoſe buried under the Rubbiſh of this Tower of <hi>Shilo.</hi> Let <hi>Phinehas</hi> execute Judgement, that the Plague may be ſtaid. Let the Prieſt cry mightily betwixt the Temple, and the Altar; and the peoples amendment ſay <hi>Amen.</hi> Let the Rich Scribe and Phariſee bring their Talents; the middle ſort their Shekels, the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:133593:12"/> poor Widow her two Mites, to provide Bread and Triacle; Meat and Medicine; Peſt-houſes, and Keepers; and all other Materials which may ſerve Religiouſly to Exorciſe the Spirit of Deſperation out of thoſe whom the deplorable Mortality have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forc'd to want Doctor, Apothecary, Chirurgeon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or another <hi>Lues Epidemica,</hi> an Univerſal dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Trading, has put into the Furnace of Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and made like <hi>Narciſſus</hi> in <hi>Tacitus, Certa ſibi pernicies, ſeu Britannicus rerum, ſeu Nero potiretur;</hi> Fore-ſeeing approaching deſtruction to them, and their Families, if not by the Plague, yet by Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine; <hi>Surgunt indocti &amp; coelum rapiunt, cum nos cum Doctrina nostra mergimur in Gehennam.</hi> The unlearned practical Chriſtian rakes Heaven by violence, whilſt the ſpeculative Maſter in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> with all his <hi>Quidli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bets,</hi> and <hi>Quodlibets</hi> of a dead Faith, is plung'd into Hell.</p>
            <p>Thoſe <hi>Heathen,</hi> that were deſervedly Renown'd in their ſeveral Ages, for Improving the Light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to a ſevere vertuous Life, ſhall find the Day of Judgement an eaſier-to-be entreated and propitious Audit, then the Prophane, Diſſolute, or Scra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, penurious Profeſſors of the Doctrine of the Holy Jeſus; who will not be perſwaded to work out their Salvation with Fear, and Trembling; Although they may have a Light to their Feet, and a Lanthorn to their Paths, the glad Tidings of the Goſpel; which ſhines clearly, and beautifies every corner of our <hi>Horizon.</hi> This made <hi>Cyrus</hi> the <hi>Perſians</hi> Death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed ſoft, and ſtufft his pillow with Down; I have been Merciful, and Munificent, caſt continually a good
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:133593:13"/> Aſpect, and made it my buſineſs to benefit, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive the felicity of all Regions under my Influence; and now I expect to finde favour, and receive my Dividend of his Loving-kindneſs; who is a great God, from whom Men challenge their Original, and Mercy flows in a deep Channel, and perpetually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing Streams. <hi>O ſi hoc eſſet pugnare!</hi> O how hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py might we count our ſelves if this were to fight! hum'd out the ſleepy Souldier, inamour'd of his Neſt; ſtretching his hands over his head, and open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his eyes by halves. <hi>Balaam,</hi> an Inchanter, wiſh'd that he might die the death of the Righteous, and that his laſt end might be like his. (He durſt not curſe <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and in thoſe dayes 'twas not the faſhion to curſe themſelves) But not a ſyllable fell from him ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing an inclination (not ſo much as a whimſical Velleity) to live the Life of the Righteous. But not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the <hi>Aſs</hi> was ſmitten three times, yet ſhe deſerv'd better of her Maſter, then either that ſon of <hi>Beor,</hi> or any of the ſons of <hi>Belial</hi> do of their God; <hi>For though ſhe turn'd aſide out of the way, cruſh'd his foot against a Wall, and at laſt fell under him;</hi> yet ſhe has a far better Apologie for her ſelf, then the preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſinner; <hi>Numb.</hi> 22.30. <hi>Am not I thine Aſs?</hi> A du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful acknowledgment of property; <hi>Upon which thou haſt ridden ever ſince I was thine unto this day;</hi> A frequent ſervice, and probably for a conſiderable part of the Life of that ſhort-liv'd <hi>Animal; Was I ever wont to do ſo unto thee?</hi> 'Twas a rare contingent, a ſingle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, no incorrigible fault, no inveterate Jadiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; <hi>And he ſaid, Nay.</hi> A great truth ſure, that anger had not the face to deny. If God be God, then ſerve
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:133593:13"/> him; ſet reſolutely upon the whole duty of Man. Open your hands wide unto the poor and needy. <hi>Thou ſhalt do no murder.</hi> No, why then does <hi>Abels</hi> bloud ſume up into the third Heaven, and ſue an Appeal againſt malicious execrable <hi>Cain? Homo Homini Deus,</hi> is no repeal'd Statute, though vanity and ſordidneſs wave the Reading upon it. <hi>Am I my Brothers keeper?</hi> This froward and contumacious Anſwer was given; But trace the Dialogue a little further, God had no ſooner examin'd the cauſe, and pronounc'd, <hi>Curſed art thou from the Earth;</hi> But the Murtherer makes this rueful Reflection, <hi>My puniſhment is greater then I can bear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Forum nactus ſylvam ſuam, Teſtem mortuum, Appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torem Umbram, Carnificem Culpam, Judicem Deum: Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> is the Shire-houſe, thoſe who die for default of ſeaſonable Adminiſtrations Witneſſes, Conſcience the Accuſer, God the Judge, the Devil the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Semper ego Auditor tantum, nunquamne reponam?</hi> Shall I hear Sermon after Sermon, and not make my life the practice of Piety?</p>
            <p>Turn over Volumes of Devotion, and not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted? Walk through Hoſpitals, and never merit the truly Honourable ſtyle of a Benefactor? Make thy Cheſt ſweat, whilſt the Poor quake for cold? My ſin, and luxury Hydropick, while the indigent ſtarve? Wallow in the complacency of Honour and Riches, when my Saviours ſide is pierced through with a ſpear? His forgotten and deſpiſed Members cry out, O my head, my head! My heart, my heart! And pine, and languiſh, and die. God is not mocked:
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:133593:14"/> and God forbid but that we ſhould be able immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately to digeſt the ſincere Milk of the Word, <hi>S. Jam.</hi> 1.27. <hi>Pure Religion and undefiled before God, even the Father, is this; To viſit the Fatherleſs, and Widdows in their Afflictions, and to keep himſelf unſpotted from the World.</hi> And then, <hi>Procul hinc, procul ite Prophani!</hi> I am none of your Tribe, ye <hi>Nimrods,</hi> ye mighty Hunters, and Unſatiable Birds of prey! And <hi>Nabal,</hi> I magnanimouſly defie you, in the words of the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 18. <hi>Yea, a man may ſay, Thou haſt Faith, and I have Works; Shew me thy Faith without thy Works, and I will ſhew thee my Faith by my Works.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:133593:14"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133593:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133593:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
